<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon profitably preached in the church within her Maiesties honourable Tower, neere the citie of London  ...</title>
            <author>Anderson, Anthony, d. 1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 571</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108526</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844184</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844184</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8973</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19296)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8973)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 165:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon profitably preached in the church within her Maiesties honourable Tower, neere the citie of London  ...</title>
                  <author>Anderson, Anthony, d. 1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[104] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Walde-graue, and are to be solde at the signe of the white Horse in Cannon lane ..,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1586]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Anthony Anderson.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at the Tower.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F G⁴ (G4 blank).</note>
                  <note>Title page faded and some pages stained, affecting print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8973:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8973:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Sermon <hi>profitably preached in the</hi> Church within he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Maieſties <hi>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the</hi> Citie of London.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Before the Right</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.24 21.22.</bibl>
               <p>My ſonne feare the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d and the ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g, medd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with them that are ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d tious.</p>
               <p>For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſtruction ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for who know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h the rui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON, <hi>Printed by Robert</hi> Wald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue, and are to be ſolde a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the ſigne of the white Horſe in Cannon lane.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8973:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8973:2"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>TO THE RJGHT</hi> honorable Sir <hi>Frauncis</hi> WALSINGHAM Knight, of <hi>her Maieſties moſt honorable priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,</hi> and principall Secretorie to <hi>her Highnes,</hi> ANTHONY ANDERSON <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> of Chriſts holie Goſpell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth increaſe in Chriſt our Lord, and much honour by him multiplyed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough (Right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) it ſeeme much better to heare, yea, euen to the beſt learned, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to write of ſuche argument, as by rugged enemies hardly can bee wel digeſted, whoſe ſharpened toongs inable to further hurte, as burning coales doe ſeeke to ſcorch the godly: yet conſidering that in ſo honorable a place I had pronounced the Sermon following, and by ſo manye earneſt and godlye perſons eftſoones deſired
<pb facs="tcp:8973:3"/> to penne the ſame, I rather conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at laſt, to abide a preſente brunt, (ſheltered vnder mightie protection) and to diſcouer in part the Popiſh ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie, for the benefit of many: then cowardly for feare of ſome Romiſh ſtorme, to thruſt ſo bright a ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a darkening buſhell. And bethin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king (as conueniency asketh) on who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to craue a ſecond ſhield for this my ſo ſpent time, your Honour firſt came vnto minde: to whoſe goodnes I am not ſmally bounde, for that benefite, which earſt by your honourable mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes I did attaine. In regarde whereof, though farre vnable to render ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, or approching meaſure ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, I reſt, not debarred of former purpoſe, to preſent ſuch ſhort pay, in parte of aunſwere to further debt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured the rather by the well knowne godlineſſe in your lowly breſt, which can and doe content your ſelfe many times with a Mite, from a well min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Widowe, though muche ſtore of treaſure cannot ballaunce your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. My will is much, but my wealth
<pb facs="tcp:8973:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> is ſmall, yet ſometimes ſmall pearles for their purenes, are accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted worth ſome greater ſtones of more glorious ſhewe. A twofolde ſuite to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour I haue for this, to ſay: that your wiſedome woulde not onely accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye your good liking of this my bold enterpriſe, but alſo to vouchſafe your godlye ayde againſt ſuch <hi>Romiſh Riots,</hi> as may percaſe conſpire by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulte, againſt this ſimple truth. For though their ſhows be not all vnſeem lie, yet their deedes do approue thoſe of them which that way be abſolute, to bee in this moſt horrible murther and ſacrylege, by ſuch <hi>Sauage Treaſon,</hi> more then <hi>Reſolute.</hi> And therefore ought to bee cenſured with <hi>Eſay</hi> the Prophets ſentence.<note place="margin">Eſay. 26.10.</note> 
               <hi>Shewe mercie to the wicked, yet he will not learne righteouſnes, but in the lande of vprightnes hee will doe wickedly, and will not conſider the great &amp; mightie hand of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of whoſe craftines to deceiue, we may not (God graunt that we bee not) by ouer-ſeeing them (not with inſight neceſſary) be drawne ſecure of
<pb facs="tcp:8973:4"/> our ſafetie,<note place="margin">Ioſu. 23.13.</note> while they harbour in our boſomes. For <hi>Salomon</hi> doth ſommon our ſuruey of ſuche with ſharpe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt,<note place="margin">Prouerb. 26.24.25.</note> ſaying: <hi>He that hateth, will coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeite with his lippes, but in his heart hee layeth vp deceite. Though he ſpeake fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably beleeue him not, for he beareth ſeuen abhominations in his heart.</hi> But yet heere is comfort: <hi>Hatred maye bee coueredly deceite: but the</hi> Malice thereof <hi>ſhall bee diſcouered in the congregation.</hi> No better witnes can be of Gods truth for this, amongſt ſo many honourable Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, then your Honor, as to whom (for the diſcouerie of the preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling hate in the <hi>Catholike Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines</hi>) (bent againſt the ſacred ſtate and perſon of the Lordes annointed, our Soueraigne <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) the Lorde from aboue hath allotted you the height of ſuch honour, and the paine of this <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> to ſound the depth, &amp; by ſeaſonable ſearch ſurely to finde out, aſwell the chiefe of the deepeſt dooers in this their moſt bloudy at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt: as wiſely to weigh vp the huge bulke, and holde <hi>Ancker</hi> of all their
<pb facs="tcp:8973:4"/> traiterous Conſpiracies. And as our heartes are inflamed with heapes of praiſes vnto God for this (as many as fear the Lord, &amp; loue their own ſafety) ſo were it impoſsible to ſuppoſe, that ſuch faithfull Subiectes, could bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> continuall praier to God, in our <hi>ſole mediatour Chriſt,</hi> for the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie increaſe of godly wiſedome, grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous honour, and heauenly felicity, to the borde and bodies of ſuch ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Senators,</hi> whoſe Honours deepely regarding the daungers imminent, brought in this perillous ſtorme, ſo wiſely by diuine Councell, laide pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent hande vppon the helme of our ſtately ſhippe, as by the ſtill and moſt ſweete pirre of coeleſtiall windes,<note place="margin">Eccle. 10.20.</note> ſhee ſpeedilie (but miraculouſly) cut tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the <hi>Roaming loftie Seas,</hi> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waies croſſing, in ſuppoſe to ſound and ſinke the ſame. But by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly prouidence (in theſe honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Mariners diligence) our ſhippe of ſtate, with her <hi>owner of high Maieſty,</hi> yea &amp; her whole fraught of <hi>Christia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> peace and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon tranquillity, floteth aloft
<pb facs="tcp:8973:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> with ſingular honour (the Lord ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bee eternally praiſed) and in the prime of their wiſhed tide, hath put the <hi>Bul</hi> &amp; his <hi>Briggets</hi> to flight, which were prepared for her decaye. Nowe may <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſay, and that truely: <hi>Except the Lord had bene of our ſide, we had ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly periſhed.</hi> But this is the Lordes owne doing, and let it bee ſtill marueilous in our eies.</p>
            <p>And herehence <hi>Engliſh Iſraell</hi> praye thou to God hartily, and turne effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to the Lorde thy God,<note place="margin">Hoſea. 14.</note> truſt no more in <hi>Aſhur,</hi> nor in thine owne ſtrength, for doeſt thou not ſee, that death &amp; thy deſtruction was entered the <hi>Preſence,</hi> where neyther barbed horſe, or Canno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhot could haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed? watch &amp; pray, for Satan is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead, &amp; the <hi>Pope</hi> with his, do yet hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to preuaile. <hi>Open your gates, ye Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and lette the king of glory enter in:</hi> ſo ſhall you bee ſafe in your Courtes, and your in-ſight ſhall bee bright as the Sunne, and then you ſhall ſee, and bee bolde to ſay with the Prophet, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe wicked <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:5"/> of <hi>Rome</hi> by ſea and lande (the <hi>Iudas Ieſuits</hi> &amp; their reconciled) which counterfeite the forface of fined ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, are in truth by Touch, not better mettall, then the ruſt of yron: <hi>Euen rebellious Traytors, walking craftely, Braſſe and yron. They are all deſtroyers. The bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows are burnt, the lead is conſumed in the fier. The founder melteth in vaine:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 6.27.28.29.30.</note> 
               <hi>for the wicked are not taken away. They ſhall call them reprobate ſiluer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the Lord hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the ſage headed ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the depth of the popiſh profeſſion, and recorde their precious practiſe from firſt till now. And hereto adioine the clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the Prince, the labours of the preachers, the loue to win by pollicie in the Counſell, and forgette not the prayers of the iuſt, for their conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which ſtill ſeeke our confuſion and ſay as thou ſeeſt (if thine eye bee cleare) whether our <hi>Abſolute Papistes,</hi> be not <hi>Reſolute Rust,</hi> as before is ſaid? For ſurely our moſt gracious Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> with her pitifull <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie,</hi> cannot melt, their <hi>ſacrylegious</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:6"/> malice againſt her long ſuffering per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but euen now after ſo many bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed benefites from the Lord, by her Maieſtie beſtowed vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; vs in common (were it but our long poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed peace) the degenerate brattes of this fertile ſoile, doe with eagre moode hunt in hungre, the innocent bloude of her ſacred boſome: whoſe Romiſhe thirſt, cannot bee quenched except their <hi>Romulus,</hi> drinke carowſe in her guiltles bloude. The blowing bellows of gods holy ſpirit, &amp; worde (the godly preachers) cannot make pure that which is but droſſe: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſpende their liues in their labors, al in vaine, vppon theſe <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts:</hi> Or hath the apt matter by skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full art, more ſpeedely to melte the mettal, to ſay: the godly pollicy of the moſt honorable Councell with theſe ſo wicked menne any better ſucceſſe: For in recompence of their honours good pollicie to procure theſe: they may happely find (could they poſſibly lend them hearing) that the ruſt of theſe <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> woulde rather ſeek to
<pb facs="tcp:8973:6"/> win a <hi>Ioab</hi> in <hi>Dauid</hi> his Court,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 14.2.30.</note> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtill fauour &amp; ſparing, then by any their poſſible power they can ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply be brought to Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. But ſtill theſe Catholiques labour to harden ſome, but to hinder moe, &amp; they allure many (not of the worſt calling) to draw away the faith of the moſt from God, and loyalty from her Maieſty, if ſo they could, and therfore our <hi>Recuſants</hi> refuſe their preſence, to the holy word and ſacraments which is the prefixed purging fornace, from a forced droſſe, whatſoeuer. But now at laſt perceiuing all their hope to be at end, they bend their ouerbold bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery in wickednes againſt her Maieſty &amp; this her highnes la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of vprightnes. Certes, in reſpecte of our purpoſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them the lande is vpright, &amp; in compariſon with them and their Antichriſtian gouernement, it is the Lande of righteouſnes: where the Goſpell is ſincerely Preached, the Lordes Sacramentes in ſubſtaunce ſoundly adminiſtred, and the ſeate of holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (eccleſiaſtical &amp; ciuil)
<pb facs="tcp:8973:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> in all chriſtian ſorte erected and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. But yet when we conſider our <hi>Caſe</hi> with Gods Iuſtice, wee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge great cauſe of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie, with the whole lande, as did the Prophet <hi>Hoſea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſea. 4.1.2.3.</note> for the inhabitants thereof. In whoſe time muche wickedneſſe, great ignoraunce, and wilfull contempt of knowledge did ouerflowe the coaſt. Carnality and bloudgiltines bare a mighty ſway, with an heaping togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſinnes, euen bloude touched bloud. viz. No ſpare of kinred, or ceaſe from horrible crueltie. O Lord, farre be this blott from thy choſen nation of Englande. But in reſpecte of your Romiſhe reconciliation, wee confeſſe very many by you are made lame, and wickedly halt (which ought not once to limpe) before God, and to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, whoſe wickednes doe cauſe our dread of an heauye <hi>Cenſure,</hi> and the more: becauſe your preſent practiſe is a threat from the Lord, of a direful daye, if our ſpeedye <hi>Repentaunce,</hi> and faithfull prayers, ſtand not in the gap before him.<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.23.</note> But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
<pb facs="tcp:8973:7"/> (yee forraine and domeſtical <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains</hi>) we firmely hold not <hi>Dauid</hi> and his ſubiectes. The Lorde will protect his Annointed,<note place="margin">Pſal. 20.21. Pſal. 2.</note> and conſerue her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and ſtate vntill the day of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, and ſhee ſhall with increaſe in muche honor, continue the laſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of that day, maugre the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of your might, the Stratageams of Satan, and the furious ſonnes of perdition, by him ſent: her to deſtroy. And alſo Chriſts holy word, with her ſacred ſeat, and this moſt honorable Regiment ſhall in England ſtill abide till the ſame day of his determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though <hi>Reſyn</hi> &amp; <hi>Romeliah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 7.3.4.5 6.7.8.9.</note> in <hi>wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hope</hi> for the future <hi>Tabeall.</hi> hunt now to make a breach in our <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> &amp; thereto perſiſt to doe their beſt. Againſt all their wicked and moſt peſtilent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. O Lorde of hoaſtes, and father of Councells,<note place="margin">Pſal. 20.9.</note> ſaue thou our <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> and heare vs for her, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer wee call vpon thee: O eternall father, let thy holy ſpirit dwell in her (our head vnder thee) ſo ſhall wee her true and louing members, in godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:8973:8"/> and peace, long enioy her: which is the heart of all our deſire. And di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte O Lorde our heartes and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers as mourning Doues, to keepe vs Innocent from this great offence: But make vs wiſe as Serpentes, to bende our backes to her in godly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience: Our bodies and our beſt to her defence: Our Soules, and ſelues to ſing and ſounde thy praiſe, for this thy miraculous preſeruation of her Maieſtie, and this thy Church and Realme, in Chriſt our Lorde wee beſeeche thee. And here right Honorable I ceaſe to deteyne you crauing pardon to this, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for this, and protection as it may ſtande with godlineſſe, and the ſafety of your Honour, that my labour maye more boldely aske the Conſult, of all Satannicall conſorts. <hi>Why doe you gentyles rage &amp;c.</hi> God that is Eternall, Almightye, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull, and onely wiſe, ſigne your Honour with your allotted propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in theſe his Fatherly graces, and ſtall you longe in honour and
<pb facs="tcp:8973:8"/> godlineſſe, to liue a Godly gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour with others lyke, vnder her Maieſtye, whoſe lyfe the Lorde prolonge to her and our felicitye in him, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours humbly to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund,</hi> Anthony Anderſon.</signed> 
               <dateline>London <date>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, 30. 1586.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8973:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8973:9"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Why doe the Gentiles rage, and the people murmure in vaine. <bibl>Pſal. 2.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the firſt of our holy labors <hi>I</hi> beſeech you let vs conſider that euery good gift deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from aboue, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in full perſwaſion of our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers loue towards vs through Ieſus Chriſt his onely Sonne, Let vs faithfully by ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest prayer crye for his holy ſpirite to his vniuerſall Church, and euery part thereof: and namely to this Church of England and Ireland &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why doe the heathen rage, and the people imagine, murmure, &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate, with turbulent Spirites vpon great miſchiefe, yet all in vaine.</hi> For neither haue they cauſe ſo to frette and fume, or canne they poſſiblye bringe to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which ſo wickedly they haue in
<pb facs="tcp:8973:10"/> their banded conſultations confirmed by concluſion.</p>
            <p>The words are of <hi>Dauid</hi> the Lords annoynted, king of <hi>Iuda,</hi> beſette with ſundry enemies, hatefull at his honour, and hautely deuiſing which waye to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronize his excellencye, but for that they were too weake at home they banded themſelues with forren mates abroade, ſo as they might the ſooner at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ende of that their wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: Namely his home-dwelling <hi>Iewes,</hi> aſwell of his Courte as Country raiſed rebellion, erecting an other king a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him (euen <hi>Abner</hi> a Noble man in the land ſet vp the ſonne of <hi>Saule</hi> called <hi>Iſhboſeth</hi> and hee raigned two yeares in <hi>Iſraell</hi>) The <hi>Philiſtines</hi> they bent their ſundry battailes alſo againſt <hi>Dauid,</hi> &amp; both beſet themſelues to his decay: But this man of God heroically harted, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of his ſtate for his election, and therefore of his ſtaye of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, penneth this Pſalme to his comfort, and to the Churches inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for all times to come, declaring his reſt in Gods decree, whoſe holy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:8973:10"/> is euer ſtretched out which his mighty ſtrength for euery his annointed. The euent aunſweared according his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation:<note place="margin">2. Sam. 3.28.</note> For not onely <hi>Abner</hi> is ſlaine by an other lyke himſelfe, but alſo <hi>Iſhboſeth</hi> that turbulent pretenſed king, ſuffered ſlaughter by two of his captaines in his bedchamber, who yet for their Treaſon to their Lorde, and maiſter (For the Lorde wilbee reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of euerye Traytour,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 4.</note> whether it bee agaynſt the ſoueraigne Prince, or beloued maiſter) they were both ſlayne by the Kings commaundement. And the <hi>Phyliſtines, Ammonytes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 5.24.8. &amp; 10.</note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morites,</hi> and the forrayne Nations, mightely by <hi>Dauid,</hi> (Nay, by the LORDE for <hi>Dauid</hi>) were ſlaine in battaile.</p>
            <p>This Pſalme is alſo Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, foreſhewing the malice of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, agaynſt the Lordes Chriſt, in the action of our redemption, by the Iewiſhe people, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Prince <hi>Herode, Pylate</hi> and the Romayne power in <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> And it remayneth to ſignifye to
<pb facs="tcp:8973:11"/> all chriſtian kinges, and Potentates, what they are to looke for at the hands of wicked men, at home and abroade, if once they bende their beſt, to ſet forth Gods glory. Though many auncient hiſtories in the daies of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times, may proue this, yet neede we no other ſearch for teſtimony hereof, then the preſent viewe of Sathans en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour, in the freſh traiterous attempt of this newe conſpiracy, by theſe ſinfull Sataniſtes the Popiſhe gentiles (I meane the Romaine confederates and our Engliſhe Italienated Papiſtes) part of which the axe of Iuſtice, hath diſcerned and cut off, and the reſt doe yet attende, as ready to their deſerued hire. Whoſe harts the Lord in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye (according to his good pleaſure) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to repent: whoſe heads and hands, with the remenant of their curſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, here and beyond ſea, whether no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or ignoble: I hartely pray to God and his Magiſtrates, that they maye bee ſignes (For they hung redde En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes) to the terrour of all turbulent Traytours for his holy names ſake.
<pb facs="tcp:8973:11"/> 
               <hi>Why doe the heathen rage &amp;c.</hi> This text doth offer vs this diuiſion: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt it declareth vnto vs the nature of their conſpiracy. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And Secondly that their attemptes is all in vaine. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracye ſhall beſt bee ſeene, if wee firſt looke vpon the perſones that purpoſe ſo wicked an indeuour: and then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will offer vs, the viewe of their decree.</p>
            <p>The perſons were of ſundry nations, but one in purpoſe and profeſſion, that is to ſaye, to bereaue good <hi>Dauid</hi> the Lordes annointed, both of kingdome and life. So is the trayterous attempt preſent, againſt the ſacred Maieſtie of God and our gracious ſoueraigne his annointed <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by the Popiſhe combineds, Romaine confederates, and our Engliſhe Italienates (both Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours to God and her Maieſtye) and in their Religion very Heathens, and not other. So as wee may rightly ſaye of them, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayde of thoſe: <hi>Why do the infernall Heathen of the Weſt-church, riſe vp in tumult, and
<pb facs="tcp:8973:12"/> conſpiracie, againſt the Lorde and agaynſt his Chriſte, our gracious Ladye, and onely Queene of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Papiſtes woulde bee counted Catholiques in reſpect of their mother that ſtrumpet of <hi>Rome,</hi> but beeing her children, they are therefore <hi>Heathen</hi> and not of the common weale of the chriſtian <hi>Iſraell.</hi> It is no hard labour to finde the <hi>Romanistes</hi> ſtill to remaine heathen <hi>Gentyles.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And firſt by the place and Churche whereon they reſt. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly by the practiſe in profeſſion of the auncient gentles, whoſe ſteppes they treadde in greedy purpoſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And laſt of all by the permanent accomptes, whiche the GOD of heauen doth make of ſuch.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the place: <hi>Rome</hi> it is, the roote of all euill: the mother of theſe men: whiche bragge to beare her name: ſhee is by the Scriptures, and approued fathers ycleaped by the name of <hi>Babylon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Babylon.</note> A Citie not onely of the <hi>Gentyles,</hi> but of <hi>Heathen</hi> profeſſion,
<pb facs="tcp:8973:12"/> Idolatrous religion, and prepared to confuſion. And for the very lyke ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes, <hi>Rome</hi> beareth her name, that the godly ſhoulde beware of her. The Scriptures doe alſo call her <hi>Babylon</hi> in the Reuelation, and diſcouereth her aſwell by her ſcituation,<note place="margin">Reuel. 13.17.18 &amp;c.</note> as Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power, and Heatheniſh prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe in the Churche of GOD. The Fathers doe lykewiſe ſo terme her, as <hi>Auguſtine, Hierome, Prymaſius, Bernarde,</hi> and others.<note place="margin">In Pſal. 44. in praefat. lib. de Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu Sancto. Reuell. 16.</note> Shee is that whoriſhe harlotte whiche bringeth out the baſtarde broode of heathen Poperye: whoſe religion is deſcry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> to bee not other then ſpirituall fornication,<note place="margin">Lib. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. 4.</note> and all her Children to bee ſealed vp in her gentility.</p>
            <p>Of neceſſitye therefore the Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Papiſtes, Children of this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond beaſt, muſt bee of her: ſecond <hi>Babilonians,</hi> not for their ſcituation, but for their gentile profeſſion, which what it is, the Apoſtle <hi>Paule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. 1.23.25.</note> doth tell vs to the <hi>Romaines,</hi> ſaying: when they thought themſelues wiſe, they became
<pb facs="tcp:8973:13"/> fooles and turned the glorye of God, to the mortality of menne, and beaſtes, and hys infallible truth, to a manyfeſt lye, ſeruing creatures, ſo forſaking the Creator, whiche is bleſſed for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The Papiſtes ioyne, full, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen handes with their former fathers in the practiſe of this gentilitye, for no <hi>Paganiſme,</hi> is more pregnaunt then Poperye, in the inuention of forraine Pettye Gods, and will-worſhippe, or more groſſe Idolaters, ſeruing either liuing creatures, or deade ſtockes, and therefore worthely (this proued by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration) wee maye ſecondly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them to bee Heathen gentiles. The Popiſhe Churche doth ioye in this gentilitye, ſhee maketh choyſe therefore of creatures both ſenſible, and ſenceleſſe, namely the ſpirites of Saintes, and the Images of their ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy forme.</p>
            <p>For the Saints, their worſhippe is no leſſe to them, then if they were our God, they inuocate their names with the perſwaſion onely dewe, to the
<pb facs="tcp:8973:13"/> eternall father, and moſt wickedly they giue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of our moſt louing Chriſt, to a painted croſſe of ſiluer, woode, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubſtaunce. Doth not their confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Popiſh Chriſtianitie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> councels of <hi>Trident,</hi> wel declare the ſame? What meaneth elſe theſe manner of praiers to the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> in that blaſphemous Hymne, <hi>Aue Maris ſtella,</hi> and the lyke to the ſigne of the Croſſe, and in ſundrie other places, where contrary to their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon aſſertion they endeuour to make both that holie virgin, and the prophane piece of wood, not mediators of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, but workers and giuers of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? For thus you are there taught to pray: <hi>Haile ſtarre, &amp;c. poure thou peace into vs, ſo looſe thou the bonds and chaines of ſinners, bring thou light to the blinde, driue thou awaye our euils, and procure to vs all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vſe thy motherly aucthority, ſhew thy motherly power, lette thy Sonne heare our praiers by thy mediation, O Virgin pearleſſe, the meek amongſt all, make thou vs meeke and chaſte, giue thou vs a pure life, prepare thou
<pb facs="tcp:8973:14"/> vs a ſafe paſſage, &amp;c.</hi> Againe: <hi>Saue vs, and ſaue al others with vs, we beſeech thee for euer.</hi> And to euerie Croſſe in any Church,<note place="margin">Chemnic. part. 3.156. a.</note> in the day of the Croſſes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altations, you are taught to pray thus: <hi>Hayle thou croſſe our only hope, this time of the paſsion, increaſe righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes in the godly, and giue pardon vnto ſinners.</hi> Again to the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> in this blaſphemous praier. <hi>Gaude flore virginali, &amp;c. <hi>As the Sun cauſeth the light of the day, euen ſo out of al que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion doeſt thou (O</hi> Mary) <hi>cauſe al the world to ſhine, through and with the fulneſſe of thy light &amp; peace. O</hi> Mary <hi>mother of God, bee thou vnto vs the right waye, and eternall ioy, and euer bend thine eares to heare vs.</hi>
               </hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe (beloued) ſufficient be ſaide for this point, by and from the Papiſtes owne ſtore, to ſhew that they remaine reſolute <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> that is meere Heathen and Gentile Papiſtes. But what accompt can y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord make of ſuch, but as of their elder parentes,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.</note> which were without the couenants of promiſſe, eſtranged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the life of God, &amp; vtterly without Chriſt &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:8973:14"/> God in this world, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may right<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly conclude w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good father,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 44.</note> that they are Citizens of <hi>Babylon,</hi> &amp; ſo make all that ſticke to them, namely, to forſake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde which made them, &amp; to worſhip y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> image, which their own ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds haue filthily faſhioned: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſts I ſay, are (as other Gentiles vtterly without God, which is plainly proued by <hi>S. Iohn</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle: <hi>Whoſoeuer</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth the doctrine of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 2 9.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not in his doctrin hath not god:</hi> but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſt (&amp; euery papiſt) doth tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe &amp;c. &amp; doth not abide, &amp;c. <hi>Ergo</hi> the papiſt hath not God: is therefore as his fellow gentile, void of Chriſt, &amp; the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of ſaluation in him. That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſt doth tranſgreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of Chriſt, is moſt appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in our papiſts in this To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer now worthily impriſoned &amp; in their fellowes gone to death by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſerued. The doctrine of Chriſt is both general &amp; particular. The generall doctrine is: they which worſhip God,<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.</note> muſt worſhip him in ſpirit &amp; truth. The papiſts daily tranſgreſſe this: for their chiefe woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip conſiſteth in hypocriſie, and fayned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> doctrine and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts<note place="margin">Math. 15.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:15"/> of men. Vz. not conſonant: but all or moſte againſt the commaunde of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God. For Chriſtes particular doctrine take this for an inſtant. <hi>Giue vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> that which appertaineth vnto <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </hi> But the Papiſt doth of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious purpoſe tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſe this doctrine: therefore hee hath not God. To <hi>Caeſar</hi> doth belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g amidſt many things, at leaſt his proper lands, and naturall life: yet our <hi>Romaine</hi> Catholikes will affoorde our ſoueraigne <hi>Caeſar</hi> neither of both: but with bloodie heartes bent againſt God, meditate, conſpire, bande, conſult, proclaime,<note place="margin">Math. 25.3.4. Luc. 19.14.</note> and bray out againſt theyr Soueraigne the Lords annointed: <hi>We wil not haue this <hi>Woman</hi> to raigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs, ſhe is the heire, come let vs kill her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 21.38 Luc. 20.14.</note> 
               <hi>and lette vs take her inheritance, let vs breake their bands of doctrine, and cordes of Imperiall commaund, and ſet vp the ſonne of <hi>Tabeall,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>or the mother <hi>Athalia,</hi> and make a breach in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> for vs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 7.</note> But to ſay all their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour at a word: Theſe Catholiks ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, and by the Popes poyſon Italie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, do endeuour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> her Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſtie,
<pb facs="tcp:8973:15"/> and deſtruction of this kingdome all in one moment. Therefore they haue in vnnaturall ſort tranſgreſſed Chriſtes moſt holy doctrine, and ſet themſelues moſt wickedly to worke their peſtilent will, euen oppoſite to his commaunde. For as he ſaith to al, <hi>Giue to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> the Catholike Traytors ſay to al theirs <hi>Take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Queene</hi> your <hi>Caeſar,</hi> both lande and life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, neither doe they abide in that truth, which the auncient Church of <hi>Rome</hi> receiued, &amp; a great time faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully did holde,<note place="margin">Rom 12.1. Chriſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 1. tom.</note> as they were taught by the Apoſtle: <hi>Let euerie ſoule ſubmitte himſelfe, &amp;c.</hi> (for he that refuſeth, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to his own condemnation) for their preſent practiſe ſurely proueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. Therefore we may conclude, that theſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> Papiſts, which would be called Catholikes, are vtterly without God, as were their Fathers the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles before them, and wil do the works <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their Father <hi>Satanas:</hi> namely, to lie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> murther<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 8. Eſay. 26.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to doe wickedly in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> By theſe three
<pb facs="tcp:8973:16"/> points, then (beloued &amp; honorable Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians) ye ſee that our <hi>Romaine</hi> forrain confederates, together with our <hi>Engliſh Italienats</hi> (as they are profeſſed Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes) ſo they are approoued Heathens, not for nation onely and forraine birth, but alſo becauſe of their religion, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiliſh deuiſes, and theſe bee onely they which mutter &amp; proclaime, which band with forraine foes, &amp; breake in and out at home, among their ſecret frends, this traiterous and bloody ſound: <hi>Come let vs goe kill this <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as wee haue ſworne.</hi> But Lord, bleſſe thou our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and giue her long life o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs, and with thee life for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, we humbly (ſweete Lorde) beſeech thee. Thus haue we proued the papiſt to be an heathen and fellow Gentile with thoſe his Fathers which conſpired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lordes annointed. And wee may boldly adde, that they bee far worſe then ſuche Gentiles, whoſe care is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> walke in honeſt conuerſation. For (<hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cero</hi> ſaith) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> men to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> weale, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:16"/> excuſe for his faulte,<note place="margin">Philip. 13. de reſpub. Aruſp. 1. inuect. in Catil.</note> which doth euyll demerite of the ſame, and that eache mans naturall Countrey is as a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent vnto him, which he muſt euen with death defend.</p>
            <p>Againe, if queſtion do ariſe, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons ſhoulde growe, to whome wee owe our beſt, and moſt dutie is belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging: <hi>Surely (ſaith Cicero</hi> in his <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) our Prince, our Country,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Offic.</note> 
               <hi>and our Parentes be they, to whome wee liue, or ſhoulde in all dutifull ſorte, and to theſe we are all moſt bounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> But our Catholikes are degenerate from this ciuill and gentile condition, and are begotten by theyr Father Sathanas, to bee deſpiſers of theyr Wiues and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, hatefull to their poſteritie, and natural bloud, raunging to hunt the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of this their moſte noble Countrey, and beeyng of worſhipfull race, and gentle bloud, (if none bee founde fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her) do put on Lions harts, and weapon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hemſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> claws, &amp; puft <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> finde no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> cruell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of oure
<pb facs="tcp:8973:17"/> moſt louing Lady and Empreſſe, the Lords annointed. They bend their bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie at her tender bodie, whoſe Grace, by grace from God, doth ſtay the Pope from vſurping his tyrannicall power in her Maieſties dominions.<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.7.</note> But now are we ſure that the Lorde will deliuer her, becauſe ſhe putteth her truſt in him. Saue our <hi>Queene</hi> Lord, that ſhe maye heare vs when wee haue neede to call to her for Royall aide in our affaires, for thy holie names ſake, &amp; make vs harti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to giue thee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorie therfore, throgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this our <hi>Engliſh</hi> nation. Sufficient is this diſplay for the Gentils who they be. Now it remaineth to conſider of the Treaſon and conſpiracy, whet &amp; againſt whom it is, that theſe Catholiks of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and their confederates haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed. The manner of their conſpiracie is as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former Gentils was: they mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, and medita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t home vpon g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> miſchiefe, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>roue to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:17"/> innocent <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Lordes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed. The pureſt papiſts their Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iticall Catholikes, doe returne to worke the feat, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gates of hell haue now decreed. <hi>Sauage</hi> muſt anſwer his name, and play the ſauage beaſt, in goring of her ſacred maieſty to the heart, &amp; this is the manner and chiefe matter of theyr conſpiracie, but all in vaine, thanks and immortall praiſe be euer giuen to God therefore for this. They thus cry one to another in their picked places, the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den houſes (moſt fit corners for wicked conſpiracies) <hi>Come good Catholikes, lift vp your harts, feare not the atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, it is eaſily brought to paſſe, the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nde of our federacie is mighty &amp; inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Court doth couch vs frendes, the Country hath many ready to our aid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the land is open before vs, &amp; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> our friendes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Rome</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſper in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8973:18"/> by this high attempt winne vs fame, and breake their bandes of doctrine, that doth ſo much annoy vs, and our Catholike Church, and lette vs caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their cordes of auctority, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of our pleaſures from vs: For this <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſhall no longer raign o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh Chriſtian ſubiectes, &amp; deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, do not your hearts bleede within to ſee this prepared match without: namely, the vtter deſolation &amp; finall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of your church, your peace and naturall country? Oh vntimely borne babes, which as ſwine of the Romiſh Bore, enter the Lords vineyard, to root vp the vine, &amp; to make barren this moſt fruitful ſoile. You fathers and country men, beholde in theſe men the fruite of your childrens paſſage ouer the ſeas, to ſerue or ſee tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> looke for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> beaten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> paſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:18"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norant of theſe trecheries, againſt her Maieſty &amp; realme: for if not by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, their frendes at home (no doubt) they know hereof: &amp; yet which of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do lament y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe, or haſten from amongſt them? but I pray you let vs view from <hi>Dauids</hi> words, this wicked determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Let vs, &amp;c.</hi> Here may you ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iſſue of this Catholike conſultation: <hi>Let vs breake their bands, &amp; let vs caſt theyr cords fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs.</hi> The prophet vſeth <hi>2.</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphors vſual in the holy ſcriptures: vz. <hi>bands</hi> &amp; <hi>cords,</hi> which haue their elega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſignification, as this worde <hi>vinculum</hi> is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſometime for bondage<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vinculum</hi> taken for bondage &amp;c Pſal. 107.14 16.</note> &amp; captiuity, or ſharp reſtraint or ſeruitude, as in this place: <hi>He brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of darknes &amp;c. &amp; brake their ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds aſunder .i. the gates of braſſe, and burſt the barres of iron.</hi> And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet <hi>Nahum,</hi> this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>io<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or <hi>metonomyan</hi> the Lord alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> deliuerance to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ity &amp; bondage of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Thogh I haue afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thee no more:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nahum. 1.13</note> 
               <hi>for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> he fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, &amp;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, lordſhip,
<pb facs="tcp:8973:19"/> and captiuitie, I will burſt in ſunder. And in <hi>Eſay:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 28.22. Ierem. 2.20,</note> 
               <hi>Nowe therefore bee no mockers, leaſt your (bondes or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, captiuitie or plagues) increaſe.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,<note place="margin">Secondly for godly Lawes.</note> this word <hi>Vinculum</hi> is els taken for good and godlye lawes, aſwell from God giuen, as by godly Princes eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed &amp; vred, and called bonds, for that hereby the laſhing luſts of carnall men are reſtrained, &amp; they compelled to lyue in ciuill ſort that haue not care of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian condition, <hi>Ieremy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ieremy. 5.1.</note> the Prophet, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth the wickednes of his time, that rich and poore, great and ſmall perſons, did violate the Lords lawe, none would execute iudgement, ſeeke the truth, and walke therin, that the Lord might ſpare them. Wherfore ſurmiſing that the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer men were of the worſt mindes, hee ſaid: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
               <hi>I will get me vnto the great men and will ſpeake vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> they haue kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:19"/> 
               <hi>their peaceable life.</hi> So euen in this Pſalme, by bondes, he meaneth the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of health in his how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> coardes, the regiment o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Prince, to guide them in godly obedience. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of all <hi>Paule</hi> the holy Apoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th vſe this worde <hi>Vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulum</hi> for Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tian vnitie in godly amitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> exhorting the Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſians to endeuour to keepe the vnitie of the ſpirite in the bond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce: he meane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that Gods Goſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th vs to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious to God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to our Prince, &amp; peaceable to our owne Country.</p>
            <p>Now th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> metaph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>al word <hi>coards</hi> is not leſſe ſignificant in this place:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for by the word <hi>coard,</hi> is ſometime meant (and here i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) the ground or i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heritance meaſured and aſſorted to their p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtions. So <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh in the Pſalme, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the faithfulnes of God to <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> and promiſe to their fathers, he ſaith: <hi>God hath remembred, &amp;c.</hi> ſaying, <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> will <hi>I</hi> giue the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of thine inheritance.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iſrael</hi> did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with liues, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and then
<pb facs="tcp:8973:20"/> caſt lottes for their deuided portions Alſo it is taken for ruling compulſion,<note place="margin">2. Coardes taken for authoritie &amp; comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement.</note> to abide the commaund of the ſuperiour, alluding to captiues which are chayned or coarded together, &amp; conſtrained to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, as in this our text pſalme, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other places. But what is the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence vppon all this collection? forſooth when our Catholiks as our <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles do cry: <hi>Let vs breake their bands and caſt their cords from vs:</hi> then they ſay. <hi>Let vs releaſe the catholiks of the Goſpels bondage, let vs diſſolue the preſent gouernment, ciuill and eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, let vs kil the Prince, ſpoile the cuntry, and take the lands for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.</hi> Now haue you the matter of our Catholikes, &amp; the maner of their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt againſt our <hi>Dauid,</hi> and purpoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this noble Citie, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ole regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſorow, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtorm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> argu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:8973:20"/> conſolation and time to repente, hath ſaide, it ſhal not be ſo. No gratious Father, graunt if it be thy bleſſed will, that it neuer be, but as nowe, ſo alwaies in thy great mercie, lette their trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome heades be terrible tokens to their confederates, whoſe braines do feruent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie boyle to breede our common calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The time doth nowe require, that we ſpeake alſo of the ſeconde point be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore promiſed, that is, to ſhewe howe vayne is the attempts of al ſuch Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes Papiſtes, as purpoſe battaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Father of heauen: <hi>Why doe ye meditate miſchiefe in vayne</hi> (ſayth <hi>Dauid.</hi>)</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In this ſecond part of our text, let vs obſerue firſt, howe inconſiderate the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of <hi>Dauid</hi> be, which purpoſing his ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>owe, doe not premeditate of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with comfort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uerſaries bee to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> what ſucceſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere
<pb facs="tcp:8973:21"/> verie inconſiderate: For the one ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of many frendes in <hi>Iewry,</hi> by reaſon they had ſuche colour to crowne a king of the former kinges line, namely, <hi>Iſhbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Saule</hi> his ſonne,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 2.8.9</note> and had <hi>Abner</hi> one of the mightieſt men in the lande, to be their Agent. And the forraine foes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed now their fitteſt time to make at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, when cyuill warres were riſe in <hi>Iſr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell,</hi> deeming <hi>Dauid</hi> now to be more weake, and them-ſelues to finde good friendes in the Lande againſt him: both which people had ſome ſhewe of reaſon, for theſe matters bee not of ſmall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ciuill ſeditions. But yet the parties againſt whome ought to haue beene firſt reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rded: <hi>Iſrael</hi> was taught before, and <hi>Abner</hi> could tell it <hi>Iſhboſeth,</hi> that the Lord had ſworne to remoue the kingdome from <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of<note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.9.10.</note>
               <hi>Daniel</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:21"/> done vnto <hi>Dauid</hi> eſpeci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly ſince the Lorde did ſo delight to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Iſrael<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r dayes the <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht for <hi>Iſra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam 4 8.6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.7.13.</note> and they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſeſ e it. So likewiſe our Cath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lique P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, with their forraine confederates in this their ſauage Treaſon, bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer inconſiderate, for they in hate of our moſt honorable <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eth</hi> neuer ſo much as dreame of her moſt holy God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> euen the God of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> the Lord of Heaſtes, vnder whoſe ſtandard ſhe ſtandeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant with her diſplaied banner againſt all his and her enemies: But her <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,</hi> ſeeing the weakenes of their truſt, and her power to reſt in the Lorde her ſtrength,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as <hi>Dauid</hi> then in good ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, ſo h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r highnes may now, in ſounde ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with the <hi>Pſalmiſt, <hi>Why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Catholiques, the people my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne, and the genti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>madnes: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ble miſchiefe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> whom they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Lord</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8973:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8973:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8973:23"/> God alſo, who hath mercifully ſette mee ouer them? Why doe they ſo?</hi> This queſtion <hi>Quare?</hi> is not without his double <hi>Emphaſis.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Fyrſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> queſtion is pearcing, it is much more forceable to ſay? <hi>Why doe they ſo?</hi> Then if <hi>Dauid</hi> had ſaid, but ſimply thus, <hi>The enemies doe thus rage againſt mee,</hi> for it rowſeth vp the ſences, and aſketh the ſpirites of menne a reaſon of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely endeuours. This figurate ſpeach contayneth firſt a kynde of admiration, as thus: Is it not a wonder to ſee ſuch menne ſo madde? <hi>What cauſe haue I geuen them thus to rage agaynſt me?</hi> Secondly it offereth the checke with his inuincible mate: vnto theſe incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate <hi>Catholiques?</hi> Why doe yee ſo hotly take in han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>odigie, as neuer canne th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, or canne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ger of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">2. king. 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:23"/> Hoaſtes: but you ſhall bee brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lords annoynted, who is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to cruſhe you with his Iron rodde. To the firſt <hi>Quare,</hi> then as a ſufficient <hi>Impedit,</hi> to all Popiſhe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones, and Catholique practiſers in Popiſhe treaſons, lette vs lende our eares I pray you. Her <hi>Maieſtie</hi> in the ſimplicitie of her ſoule doth demaunde of you her naturall borne ſubiects (for though her bountye hath not wrought the confederates much benefite, yet ſhe wondereth not at them ſo much) why do you my engliſh ſubiects thus riſe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt me? Are yee not my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſubiects borne? am I not your lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and lawfull Queene, anſwere me I pray you to ſatiſfie my ſelf driuen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mighty wonder for this your inſolent folly? The ſeduced Catholique with his D. <hi>Story,</hi> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>peth her <hi>Maieſtie</hi> this ſhort anſwere: we are not your ſubiectes. So ſaid ſtone of the late executed: we haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your words deſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted to die, we haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and wee are iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in deede wee are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and indite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:24"/> and condemned for. Beholde a mighty worke of God in this his holy name be alwaies bleſſed which hath to the ſhame of all Papiſtes, and the preuention of credite to that counterfaite booke by the Romiſh runagates at <hi>Rheymes</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be poſted ouer hither, wherein they will counterfeit to deny theſe men to belong to the Catholiques, with the former alſo, whiche in any ſorte, haue ſought the alteration of the ſtate or hurt to her Maieſtie: For we (ſay they) pray for the Queene of England euery daye: Oh ſubtile Sathan: but the ſtronger Captain hath ouerthrown thee, this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe is to baſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Saunders</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>und. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> books before, &amp; theſe mens voluntarye confeſſions now doe laye open thy infectuall treacherye. They haue told vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſking, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing at t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aſon again <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:24"/> Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ene you pray for, we pray alſo, if it pleaſe God to graunt her better grace: But we be not Papiſtes, our ioy is not in <hi>Mary</hi> the mother, No: we reioyce in <hi>Ieſus Christ</hi> the ſonne onely, and in his annointed our Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> as in the Lord it becommeth vs, and haue our hearts and hands ready againſt you &amp; your Queene, whenſoeuer you ſhould haue taken aſſaye of our preparation. For as <hi>Iſraell</hi> cryed againſt the <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> for the Lord, and his <hi>Gedeon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg 7.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> ſo doe we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rew Engliſhe ſubiects, cry againſt all Catholique Traytors, and their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture truſt, for the Lorde and his <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi> And he that beareth not this mind here or elſe where in any wiſe belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to her <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> whether he bee an <hi>Abner</hi> or <hi>Abyſhaye,</hi> noble or ignoble, the Lord con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ert him or confounde him, for his mercie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſake, to our Engliſh <hi>Iſraell:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> But ye haue not yet anſwered this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yea not her Maieſties ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi> ye Engliſh Emperors yes, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of you choſen into chiefe place of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of her ſecret bodye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:8973:25"/> bountye yee are largely fedde. But yet are not now: what is your reaſon? for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth Syr Preacher this it is, your Queene is by the holy father excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, and all her ſubiectes by his aucthoritie ſette at freedome from their othe of alleageaunce, and naturall bond of duetye. Is this the matter? Well: we take firſt that you graunt vs. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet,</hi> that you were borne her loyall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, and that beeing further, her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, you were ſworne to bee faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and loyall to her <hi>Maiestie,</hi> and ſo by inference, yee confeſſe that before this excommunication ſhee was your louing Miſtres &amp; your lawfull Queene alſo? Yea Syr, wee doe ſo: well then lette vs that bee good ſubiectes aſke of God, and good meu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hether any man in earth ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſubiect of his de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ince, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:25"/> that doth take vppon him to diſcharge vs, of this charge, and by what aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly his diſcharge what it is, and of what importaunce, by which ſuruey we ſhall plainly ſee, Sathan to haue ſeated Antichriſt, in the conſciences of theſe forlorne Caitiues, aboue the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. The Lord God of <hi>Iſraell</hi> it is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth al ſubiects to owe in hart &amp; performe in faithfull ſeruice all honorable duety to their ſuperiors, in theſe words, <hi>Honour thy Parents <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> which word honor requireth inward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, reuerende accompt, and harty affection from the ſoule of the inferiour and outward ſeruice with externall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and all kindes of duety, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the bond of the parties obliged. And the chiefe parent vnder God is the king or chiefe Potentate of the country as in Englande our gracious Queene <hi>Eliz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>beth.</hi> To kingly parents,<note place="margin">Pet. 2.</note> the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>aunded &amp; charged vs to giue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, tribute, obedience, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſilence, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hony ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> raigne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they be neither
<pb facs="tcp:8973:26"/> Chriſtians nor comfortable to their ſubiects, but Heathen Princes, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous kings, or cruell Tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as theſe and many ſuth other places doe proue. <hi>1. Sam. 10.25.8.11.12.13. Iere. 29.7. Exod. 21. Pſal. 20.82. Eccle. 9. Pro. 6.24. Ma. 21.21. Mar. 12.17. Luc. 20.25. Ro. 13.1. 1. Pet. 2.13.17. 1. Tim. 2.1.2.3.</hi> And the diſobedience hereto draweth Gods vengeaunce as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, and the ſcripture proueth, as the plagues of <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram:</hi> by the very hande of God from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen doe teſtifie, his hate of diſobedience in earth, to his appointed Magiſtrates. Yea, our fealtye, and allegeaunce ought to be ſuch vnto them, as we permit not an euill thought to poſſeſſe, nay, not to enter, our boſomes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m. For the byrds of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cle. 10.</note> bewray ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll reue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 18.9.</note> ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:26"/> either equall or aboue God, but forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as he is the Lorde omnipotent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all, therefore it cannot be, that man or Angell canne graunt either free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome againſt this commaunded duetye, or in any ſorte to diſcharge vs of the ſame, yet naye the leſſe that manne of ſinne, the Antichriſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> doth take vpon him in his Bulles, both thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and into <hi>Fraunce,</hi> to doe the one, and the other. And he hath hereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſotted many fine witts, and made dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into this rebellion, not a fewe, able perſons to haue ſerued her Maieſtie, in much better ſort. But I beſeech you Syr <hi>Pope,</hi> by what aucthoritye doe you diſcharge our engliſh ſubiectes of their moſte bounden dutie to her Maieſtie, their naturall Soueraigne, ſith you are but an <hi>Italian</hi> Prieſt, or Biſhop, &amp; haue no place, much leſſe ſetth Regall power in <hi>England?</hi> His friendes do aunſwere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him thus: That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee is the Vicar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> earth. Surely ſir, but not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. For the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſente, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, to the ende
<pb facs="tcp:8973:27"/> of the worlde.<note place="margin">Mar. 16.20. Hebr. 13.21.</note> And for the ciuill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, hee confirmed that Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he founde, as of olde by himſelfe eſtabliſhed, commaunding euery nation to obeye their ſuperiour powers, and to giue their King that whiche is his. Yea and Chriſt himſelfe for example to all Chriſtians, though hee bee free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it ſelfe and Subiecte to no creature, but ſoueraigne ouer all: yet both himſelfe and his <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 17.25.</note> he paid tribute money, teaching by the miracle of the fiſhe, that all poſſible meanes muſt be made, by ſea and land, of euery ſubiect bond or free, to our duety vnto our <hi>Caeſar</hi> leaſt wee ſhoulde in any ſuche ſorte offende them. And for the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall gouernement, hee neuer commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it vnto one alone, no not among the <hi>12.</hi> Apoſtles: but rather reprooued that ambition in them and ſette this downe for a lawe, that whiche of them ſhoulde hunger after he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſhippe he ſhoulde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> farre depre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hadd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:27"/> And when he ſent out to preach he gaue equall commiſſion, ſaying: <hi>Goe yee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 20.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mat. 16.15.</note> 
               <hi>and preache, and baptiſe <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth not, that Chriſt hath ſette not onely one Vycarre in his abſence till his returne: <hi>But aſcending and leading Captiuitye Captiue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 4,</note> hee hath giuen (not one gifte to one vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Paſtor, or Elder vppon the whole Churche but) giftes to menne, as that in the perſone of many, his holy ſpirite, maye raigne and rule in the heartes of all that feare him. Hee hath therefore geuen ſome to bee Apoſtles, ſome Prophets ſome Euangeliſtes and ſome Paſtours, and Teachers, that in this <hi>Aristocratia</hi> his ſpirite might go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne his Church, &amp; not in a Monarchy, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope would haue it. Neither doth that place ſo often alleaged ſerue his turne: <hi>Tibi dabo claues &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 26.</note> For beſides that theſe keyes, haue no power to ſhut vp the Pallace from the Prince, nor Royall kings from their Regall digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, or yet other men from their earth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>: But are giuen to open <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Goſpell by the
<pb facs="tcp:8973:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:29"/> office of preaching, and to ſhutte out of Gods congregation for a time, ſuche as doe continue to heare his voice, and to obey his holy commaund: So, when this promiſe was performed, it was giuen in common to al the Apoſtles with him in equality, Chriſt ſaying to them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Receiue ye (not thou Peter alone or firſt, or aboue the reſt) the holy ghoſt: whoſe ſinnes ye remit, they are remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp;c. Thus Chriſt and his Apoſtles left the ſtate of his Churche. And if it ſhould be otherwiſe, I muſt needes wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at <hi>Peter</hi> his ſoftnes, that hauing ſuch authority aboue the reſt giuen him of Chriſt, he would beare ſo baſe a mind as to ſuffer not onely his equalls to v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpe his preheminence, but his inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, the Elders in the Churche, to vſe aſmuch power in doctrine and gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Eccleſiaſticall as he. Or yet that hee woulde not excommunicat the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gall. 1.</note> for reprouing him openly before the people in <hi>Antioch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely the very reaſon w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> that as hee was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (a ſhrewde che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:29"/> he was of an heauenly ſpirit, and tooke reproofe as a medicine to that diſeaſe, and neuer ſette himſelfe aboue his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, but ioyned himſelfe with his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours for calling (yet equall in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) ſaying:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.1.</note> The Elders which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you I beſeeche, which am alſo a fellowe Elder &amp;c. <hi>Conſenior,</hi> is your vulgare tranſlation, <hi>Feede the flocke &amp;c.</hi> Not as Lordes ouer Gods hery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: but that yee may be enſamples to the flocke.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>And when that chiefe ſhepheard ſhall appeare, ye ſhall receiue an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible crowne of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note this good brethren, <hi>Peter</hi> is but a fellowe Elder with his brethren,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.20.</note> and doth ſo entitle himſelfe. And note alſo, that he referreth the name of chief, princely or heade to the onely Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearde of our ſoules <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> alone. And to conclude this point: if Chriſt gaue not any one the preheminence of all: if hee appointed not a Monarchye, but a Churche gouernement Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ticall (<hi>videlicet:</hi> to rule by ſundry) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> no larger keyes then
<pb facs="tcp:8973:30"/> the reſt, if he tooke no more vppon him then a fellowe Elder, if hee became not a comptroler of the whole Church, but was vnder the cenſure of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that did diſcerne him: how canne it come to paſſe, were hee <hi>Peter</hi> his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour (as <hi>Symon Magus</hi> doth rather challenge him) that vnder the name of <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle (whoſe limitation by Gods ſpirite was ouer the Iewes, and <hi>Paules</hi> commiſſion, rather more Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoplike ouer the <hi>Gentiles</hi>) this Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhoulde haue ſuch auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritye ouer our ſoueraigne, ſo farre diſtant from his territorye, or Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricke, as to excommunicate her <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,</hi> to diſcrownize her Royall perſon, and to releaſe her ſubiectes from the bondes of their alleageaunce, and (as it fitteth the nature of that monſtrous <hi>Hydra</hi>) to ſanctifie as ſaintes, all ſuch curſed ſoules, as woulde embrue their handes in her right Innocent bloude. The aunſwere is ſtill, becauſe hee is Chriſtes miniſteriall heade in his vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Churche, therefore hee may a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> doth excommunicate. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:30"/> and alſo depoſe her of her Crowne, and dignitye. If he bee demaunded who hath endowed him with this power, theſe miſerable Traytours ſay, it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him by <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> our Lorde, ſo ſaith the Pope himſelfe in the Canon lawe: <hi>Paſtoralis cura &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the Paſtorall care of the whole Chriſtian Churche, is by the diuine power and commiſſion laide vpon vs. Againe, <hi>De nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te credendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c.</hi> It is of neceſſity to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, that euery creature is ſubiect to the Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome:</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayne the Pope is ſette ouer all aſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll ouer all Nations as kingdomes.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. de ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>di.</note> And agayne the Pope hath power to tranſferre kingdomes at his pleaſure and to ſende one king into anothers kingdome. The Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> hath in him,<note place="margin">Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment. c. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtoral. de ie iudic. c. 2. ibid</note> the whole Monarchie of both powers, ſpirituall, &amp; temporall. Theſe bee blaſphemous and thraſonicall braggs. But this proude &amp; inſolent challenge if we confer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ieſus Chriſts</hi> modeſty &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement to his Apoſtles, we ſhall eaſily perceiue, that from him neither <hi>Peter,</hi> or <hi>Pope</hi> canne haue ſuch commiſſion. The kings of the
<pb facs="tcp:8973:31"/> nations raigne ouer them ſaith <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and they that bee great exerciſe auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye ouer them: but it ſhall not bee ſo with you, but hee that will bee chiefe amonge you let him bee your Miniſter, euen as the ſonne of manne came not to bee miniſtred vnto but to miniſter. And according to this courſe, when hee ſent them to preache into the worlde af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his aſſention, he made no one chiefe of them, to aunſwere his place of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue ouer the reſt, but reſeruing that romth to himſelfe, ſaying: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.20.</note> ſaying: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, I am with you to the ende of the worlde, hee gaue to them one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall commiſſion and place, goe yee, and preache yee the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.20.</note> baptize yee, and doe you teach them, to obſerue all that I haue commaunded you. But good chriſtians, marke wel that I ſhall ſay, and I truſt you will ſaye with me, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neither <hi>Peter,</hi> nor <hi>Pope</hi> can be Chriſts ſucceſſor to haue his whole aucthoritye ſole ouer all. The Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> doth ſaye that by the aucthoritye of Chriſt, hee is Peters ſucceſſour the Prymat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the worlde. But aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne I aſk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:31"/> by what right? If hee ſaye by the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, why did not <hi>Peter</hi> then practiſe it? or why did all the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> vntill the ſuppoſed donation by <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> not once dreame of it? And what reaſon then hath his owne Lawe, to ſhut vnder hard cenſure, ſuch as ſhal preſume this title vnto them? For the decree (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting it from <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) ſaith: <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque deſiderauerit primatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in terra, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenerit confuſionem in co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Duſt. 4. c. multi &amp; qui cunque.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall hunger after primacie in earth, ſhall finde confuſion in heauen.</hi> Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall he be numbred among the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of Chriſt, which contendeth for ſupremacie.</p>
            <p>Again, the Biſhop of the firſt or chiefe ſeat ſhall not be called, either the prince of Prieſts, or the high or chiefe Prieſt, or any ſuch like name: but onely the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> himſelfe be called vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal. And ſurely if the holy ſcriptures had giuen ſuch preheminence to <hi>Peter,</hi> and his ſucceſſors, both the firſt Church, and Councels, aſwell <hi>Nyce</hi> as <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le,</hi> of <hi>Epheſus</hi> as <hi>Calcedon,</hi> had bene ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y iniurious to the holy Apoſtle, and his
<pb facs="tcp:8973:32"/> ſucceſſors, and further not to the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in the Church onely, but alſo to their owne deſerued credites: all which time and councels (as knowing no ſuch matter) did giue prerogatiue to euerie Biſhop in his owne ſea onely,<note place="margin">Concil. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen. p. 315. c. 6. Brut Ful. 153. Eph. Synod. an. 431. c. vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timo. Concil. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. au. 450.</note> and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie Patriarke in his own prouince a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and made equall the other Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes with the Patriarke of <hi>Rome.</hi> And if they haue it by ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I aſke, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of doctrine, or place, or perſon, or one, or al? For doctrine I am ſure there is as greate difference betweene <hi>Peters</hi> doctrine and the Popes, for many yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res paſt, as is betwixt truth &amp; falſhood. As for example: <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill, but honour the king,</hi> was <hi>Peters</hi> doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine: but the Popes is, <hi>Thou ſhalt not honour, but kil the Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> if ſo thou canſt,</hi> as the Cardinals letter to that traytor <hi>Pary</hi> is moſt apparaunt. But if he ſucceede not in doctrine his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſucceſſion is of no value: yet what other ſucceſſion can he haue? By the cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill lawe it appeareth, that there bee 3. ſortes of ſucceſſion:<note place="margin">L. vlt. d. de exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot rei rend L. 1. c. in locum.</note> vz. <hi>Succeſſores Iuri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rei. muneris perſonalis.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8973:32"/>
            <p>The firſt ſorte are called ſucceſſors v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall, and theſe be as heires.<note place="margin">D. quod le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat. l. 7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. de iure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and. l. pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilegio 27. c. de decut. l. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeconde ſorte are, of matters or goodes acquyred or giuen by Legatorie meanes, and theſe bee called ſucceſſors in part, or particular.</p>
            <p>The third ſort are of perſonall giftes, &amp; theſe be called ſucceſſors in function.</p>
            <p>They now which be ſucceſſors of the firſt, or ſecond ſort, haue their right and authority of thoſe, whoſe ſucceſſors they be,<note place="margin">L. qui in Iuſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>2 c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reg <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> whether they be vniuerſall or ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. But the thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſorte haue not their ſucceſſion in r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ht of theyr anteceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, but of thoſe of whome they are choſen, and are ſo placed in theyr anteceſſors Roomes, whether it be the ſucceſſion of Magiſtrates, Tutors, Church-men, or ſuch like. For the office and place is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall, which is ſupplied with watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the ſoule. Now I demaund of the Lord Pope by what kind of ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is Chriſtes ſucceſſor, or <hi>Peters</hi> before him? Chriſts heyre <hi>Peter</hi> cannot be,<note place="margin">L. 1. d. de Herod. vend</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Lorde Chriſt lyueth for euer, and doth not reſigne his righte to hym, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anie other, neyther canne hee ſuffer
<pb facs="tcp:8973:33"/> to haue companions in his dignitie.<note place="margin">Heb. 7.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>Leo</hi> the Pope hath ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſaide this blaſphemie, that Chriſt hath giuen to <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sermone 3. de Anix. aſſ. 10. Heb. 7.24.</note> a woonderfull fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of his power. Much leſſe canne the Pope be either his ſucceſſor, or <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> in vniuerſall, or in particular, ſince Chriſt neuer gaue to him that preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, but ambition hath begot him that name, which firſt began at <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> after tooke roote at <hi>Rome.</hi> And the Councell of <hi>Calcedon</hi> doth freely affirm,<note place="margin">Conc. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon. An. 451. rent. c. 28.</note> that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had his honour not from <hi>Peter,</hi> but from the emperiall ſeat, ſaying, becauſe <hi>Rome</hi> then raigned ouer all: therefore the Fathers gaue her Church the greateſt honour, and firſt place, but nowe perſwaded by the ſame rule, we giue (ſay they) to the new <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> equall degree in honor and place, with the auncient <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the third ſort of ſucceſſion, the Pope hath naught to do therewith, for he cannot be vniuerſall ſucceſſor to him, that hath no ſucceſſour at all, but doc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſupply the office him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:33"/> extinguiſhed, but remaineth euer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent by his power and ſpirite,<note place="margin">Hebr. 13.20.21.</note> the chiefe ſhepheard of his Church, and vſeth men, his Apoſtles and Biſhops vz. preachers of his word, but as the hands by whome he ſolie gouerneth ouer all. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; preached,<note place="margin">Mar. 16.20.</note> but Chriſt wroght with them, and confirmed the worde with ſignes and wonders. Beholde (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) the preſence of Chriſt, with the labour of his Apoſtles. And to <hi>Peter,</hi> the Pope can bee no ſucceſſour: For it is a function perſonall, and taketh ſucceſſion from the election and giuer, which is not Chriſt, but ſuppoſed <hi>Conſtantine:</hi> wherefore the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Biſhop is not <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> ſucceſſour, but the Emperours, who extinguiſhing that power in himſelfe, endowed the wicked Pope therewith. But when Chriſt ſent his Apoſtles to preach the worde, and to gouerne hys Church hee did not ſette ouer them one dumb Arch-meſſenger, or Arch-apoſtle,<note place="margin">Eſay. 56.10.</note> which ſhould reſt ſnorting in his chaire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> home, and commaund all others, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome the faithfull laborers, as vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> render an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt,
<pb facs="tcp:8973:34"/> for ſuche a dumbe creature is vnworthie the name or dignitie of an Apoſtle, Patriarch, Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or Miniſter.<note place="margin">Trait. 12. 4. in Ioan.</note> And touching the promiſe, <hi>(tibi dabo)</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the Pope of that preheminence, and declareth <hi>Peter</hi> to ſignifie there the vniuerſall Church, which is founded v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on Chriſt. Wherefore he ſayth: <hi>Non ecl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abo me ſuper te. I <hi>will not builde my bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie my Church vppon thee</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, <hi>but I will build thee vpon me.</hi>
               </hi> So then the kepes by S. <hi>Augustines</hi> iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are not giuen to <hi>Peter,</hi> as to him onely or in chiefe, but with him, to the whole Church of Chriſt. But this is that Sathanicall pride of <hi>Rome,</hi> which that olde Father <hi>Barnard,</hi> ſo long ſince ſawe, &amp; reproued in theyr Biſhops, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>In times paſt ye were (contrary to <hi>Peters</hi> doctrine) Lords ouer Gods he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Barnare. epiſt. 230.</note> 
               <hi>and againſt his <hi>Coapoſtle Paule</hi> his doctrine, ye beare the ſwaye ouer the faith of the worlde, but nowe ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue added attempt, vſurping mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> tyranny againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> And what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8973:34"/> ye tranſcend the heauens, &amp; preſume to beare rule ouer the Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas they boaſt of <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the Emperor, that hee gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this prerogatiue, to be ouer the Biſhops and prieſts of the earth, as the king is ouer his Iudges &amp; to haue the temporall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer his people. Note I pray you, that by this challenge th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſecretly confeſſe, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue no ſuche power for theyr Pope by Chriſt, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t rather of <hi>Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tantine</hi> the Emperor. And who can bee ignorant y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euery priuilege is a bar againſt the vniuerſall law. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope then haue but now this priuilege to be head, &amp;c then it ſufficiently appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> before this graunt the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had no more right, then by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the councels and Church, other Patriarkes had in theyr places. Which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon conſent was, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ech patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch ſhould be the gouernor of his owne Prouince, and not to thruſt himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> anothers territory. And here obſerue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if <hi>Conſtantine</hi> could by right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this vniuerſal Church power from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is certaine, that at the
<pb facs="tcp:8973:35"/> time of this gift, the ſaid Emperor was Lorde of that hee gaue, and before this, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d this preheminence in himſelfe. For <hi>Conſtantine</hi> could not properly giue that which was not his to beſtow. And this Obiection <hi>Marſilius Patauinus</hi> laide to the Popes pride <hi>200.</hi> yeare ago,<note place="margin">Defenſ. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is. cap. 11.</note> 
               <hi>In de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretis reperitur priuilegium, &amp;c. <hi>In the decree</hi>
               </hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>it is ſaide, that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi> gaue to <hi>Sylueſter</hi> iuriſdiction vppon all the Churches in the world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Brut. Ful.</note> 
               <hi>Seing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the Pope and his cleargy doth holde this for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and ſound, it is by conſequence certain to be graunted, that the ſame <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> before this graunt, had in his power and perſon, the preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and iuriſdiction ouer the Pope, and all his cleargy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus you ſee by the holye Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Popes Canons, their owne confeſſion of graunt, natural reaſon, and ſearch into t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ter of chalenge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> neither <hi>Pete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Pope hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> alone wic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:35"/> which is inough to his condemnation, except hee better could vſe it. And you ſee that Chriſtian kings haue power in them to compel and gouern by the laws of GOD, aſwell Prieſtes as others, within their allotted kingdomes, and that from God, neither can they be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged thereof, though they committe the ſame to others.</p>
            <p>Then let vs conclude thus, that wee in this kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> beeing no parte of the Romiſh Biſhoppes territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, are not within the compaſſe of hys commiſſion, and therefore hee cannot, or may excommunicate the loweſt ſubiect of this Lande, much leſſe canne hee, or ought to dare, to excommunicate the higheſt ſoueraigne therein vnder God, our <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Lordes annointed Queene. Then looke to this you bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Cath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>likes, for as ye are borne, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> maieſtie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:36"/> For excommunication doth neyther de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Prynce of his Crowne, or yet his Subiectes of their loyaltie. Then where is your warraunt for her mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
            <p>Chriſt Ieſus ſpeaking of excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, ſaith thus of it: <hi>Lette ſuche a one whome the Church rightlye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 18.17.</note> 
               <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth out, be to thee as an heathen or as a publicane.</hi> But it is euident, that both the heathens and Publicans, were admitted their poſſeſſions, continued their offices, and were obeyed by the Church. And Chriſt Ieſus ſpirit was fo farre off from killing ſuche, that hee gaue many of them eternall lyfe, and choſe a chiefe of them into his Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe. But was not <hi>Caeſar</hi> an Heathen prince? What was <hi>Nero?</hi> but the ſame, and for <hi>300.</hi> yeares after Chriſt, the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers were no better, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raye you what is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundeth<note place="margin">Math <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:36"/> to him all ſorting dutie. And <hi>Paule</hi> knowing the rebellious nature of his brethren the <hi>Iews,</hi> doth next to faith ioyne the doctrine of obedience,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> thereby teaching dutifull ſubmiſſion to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine powers, which they moſt deadlie hated, and crowneth thoſe with godlye power, that yet were excommunicate from the Church of God. Hee exhorteth to pray for ſuche, notwithſtanding they are cut from the Church, and maye not with their heathen profeſſion, be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Chriſtian fellowſhip. And alſo he teacheth that they may well exerciſe authoritie ouer the people of God, &amp; the ſame ought to yeeld them willing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. So teacheth <hi>Peter</hi> alſo:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelues, &amp;c.</hi> he propheſieth not of Chriſtian princes to come, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth ſubmiſſion to theſe now being, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeek in mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Church of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>likes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:38"/> I thinke they will ſay yes. Then I wil offer them one inſtant of a Prince ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by the Lorde himſelfe, and yet therefore, neyther was he depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his kingdome, by Prieſt or people, or was it lawfull to ceaſe to doe him ſeruice: <hi>Saule</hi> I meane the king of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell. Samuel</hi> denounced the Lords excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying: <hi>The Lord hath caſt thee out from being king,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.23</note> 
               <hi>&amp; the Lord hath rent the kingdom of Iſrael from thee this day, and hath giuen it to thy neighbour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 28.</note> 
               <hi>that is better then thou.</hi> Here is, if yee note it, a famous excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication by the Lorde decreed, and denounced by the Prophet <hi>Samuel,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Saule.</hi> Yet for all this, God ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commaunded <hi>Samuel,</hi> or yet <hi>Samuel</hi> the Subiectes of <hi>Saule,</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll backe their ſubiection from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wfull king. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> lyfe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> And t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:38"/> pretended his death, as doe our preſent Catholikes.</p>
            <p>This aſſertion is confirmed moſte ſurely by the holie annointed <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe, and that by his oth to <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> the Counceller of <hi>Saule,</hi> and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of his bande, moſte ſharplie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouing him for his ſhamefull ſleepe in the daungerous Campe, ſaying: <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>heareſt thou not?</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 26.14</note> 
               <hi>And art thou a man? And who is like thee in Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el (ſo truſted of the king, or put in ſuche aucthoritie?) Wherefore then haſt thou not kepte thy Lorde the King?</hi> Note (that he confeſſeth <hi>Saule,</hi> notwithſtanding his excommunication, ſtill yet to bee <hi>Abner</hi> his Lorde and king alſo:) <hi>For there came one to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye the King thy Lorde. This is not well done of thee. As the Lorde lyue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> woorthie to dye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> your May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>id</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:39"/> 
               <hi>his ſeruaunt?</hi> Behold beloued, by how manye repetitions, <hi>Dauid</hi> confirmeth <hi>Saules</hi> authoritie ouer his ſeruauntes in Court, his Subiects in Campe, yea, and ouer <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe, though hee bee the heire apparaunt to the Crowne, and the ſucceſſor to <hi>Saule,</hi> euen by the Lords co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, ſo annointed.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Abner</hi> he ſaith: <hi>Saule <hi>is thy Lord,</hi>
               </hi> he ſaith not he was before he was caſte out, and before my day of annointment, but <hi>Saule</hi> is ſtill thy LORDE and king.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hee ſaith to the whole ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes and ſubiectes of <hi>Saule: <hi>As the Lorde liueth,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 26.16</note> 
               <hi>yee are guiltye of death, for your vnfaithfulnes to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Prince and Lorde, euen for this, that yee haue not doone him more faithful ſeruice, that ye haue not kept his life better to who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> this preſent yee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce, and lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:8973:39"/> place) hee is</hi> (ſayth <hi>Dauid) <hi>your Maiſter, your King, and ſtil the Lords annointed.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore your fealtie in faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is ſtill his, giue <hi>Caeſar</hi> therefore his owne. And though hee doth mee greate wrong, and ſeeketh my lyfe, and though I haue in my band <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhay</hi> and his fellowes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 26.8.</note> 
               <hi>which as men deuoide of godlineſſe, and bounden dutie, in hope of helpe by mee theyr future Prince, doe hunger the death, and offer to kill the Lordes preſente annoynted, yet neyther will I ſuffer mine to doe ſo wickedly, or yet my ſelfe to woorke his woe, neyther can I with good conſcience doe it: For hee is my Lorde, my mayſter, and my King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will therefore ſeeke to pacifie hys fury<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> petition, if ſo I maye, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> my peace, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſlaughter, aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſt my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lordes anoynted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:40"/> 
               <hi>I beſeeche thee, heare the wordes of his ſeruant. If the Lord haue ſtirred thee vp againſt me, let him ſmell the ſauour of a ſacrifice, but if the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of men haue done it, curſed bee they, &amp;c.</hi> And as wee ſee <hi>Dauids</hi> concluſion for the ſtill continuant dignitie, of the excommunicated <hi>Saule,</hi> ſo I pray you, let vs obſerue the haſt and hate of <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhay,</hi> who made no bones to ſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood of the Lordes preſent annointed, in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of dutie &amp; loue to the future prince, as more fit to raigne, and lawfully elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But let vs with holy <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſet the ſtaffe of our reſt in this his ſtay, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende the ſtate and life of our preſente Prince, and that ſo muche the more, for that our <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is bleſſed of God, as by his myraculous hand for her won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull deliuerance, he doth aſſure vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the batte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orde of the curſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8973:40"/>
            <p>Deliuer vs Lord &amp; ſaue our gracious <hi>Elizabeth</hi> for thy holy names ſake. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally note this beſotted, it is not very difficulte to diſcerne <hi>Abyſhaye,</hi> whoſe courſe is to counterfeite obedience, in ciuill ſort to the preſent <hi>Dauid,</hi> but in the meane, hee ſodainely ſelleth his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer profeſſion, and hauing an eye to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter helpe, and preſent fauour, he ſorteth his ſhewe with other ſuch, and (that of the ſodaine) as euery way bend their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, to the religion, and diſpoſition of their long hoped future Prince. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny therefore thus far ſeduced, do feather their winge againſt the preſent winde, and ſodainly ſhoote with Romiſh ſhaft, though not with cried aime, at the prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering pricke, refuſing our ſhot, or once more to ſhoote with vs, that dayly hitte the marke: Doubt not to deeme them parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt, of the future ſide, if ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to meaſure for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Abyſhay,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:41"/> loyalty, their hart is firmely ſet to wait y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time and oportunity, that their hands may ſhoote, and occaſion their crewe to ſhoute, if they ſhall deadly hit, that moſt precious But, their long deſired marke. <hi>But Lord giue them quaking handes, fearefull hartes, ſtarting bowes, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſhaftes, &amp; dreadful breaſts, yea all the ſort of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which purpoſe deadly ſhotte, at the boſome of our gracious <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </hi> And further now deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, let vs call this <hi>Quare,</hi> once againe into queſtion, ſo ſhall we ſee as before is ſaid, to our great comfort, how vnable our papiſts be, to perfect their proud at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. <hi>Quare?</hi> Why doe you ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> that ſo proudely, which neuer can of your parts be atchieued? your tumultes muſt bee ouerturned, your meditations for murther, ſhalbe of no moment, your banding ſhall ſod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> your conſult, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:41"/> whom the God of ſtrength hath ſet vp, &amp; decreed to maintaine? He wil therfore laugh at your deſtruction, wil ſpeake to you, by his anger, &amp; vexe you in his ſore diſpleaſure, he will deſtroye all you and yours, which ſought his ouerthrowe in his annointed, &amp; breake you into yeeces as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> potter doth his brittle &amp; fiery clay. <hi>Wherfore be wiſe ye Princes &amp;c.</hi> Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſtill ſpeak, &amp; alwayes hath againſt traytors hande, for his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed. The concluſion of your conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy (ye papiſts) is as theſe traytors of old. <hi>Come let vs break their bands a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſunder, &amp; caſt their coards fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs.</hi> But your practiſe, is proud, your preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is perillous but ridiculous for your purpoſe by indeuour appeareth to be no leſſe, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to bereaue our Dauid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords annointed of her life our church of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his bleſſed goſpel, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> poſſeſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mpiety &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:42"/> 
               <hi>Let vs breake their bandes, let vs caſt their coards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt beloued theſe words ioyning iuſt with our preſent Catholiques pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, doe offer vs the view of their tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous pride, and infernall confidence, which doth conſiſt in themſelues, their furniture, and multitude, euen as the heathen did of aid againſt <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Some put their truſt in horſes, and ſome in Chariots, but our truſt is in the name (the power and ſtrength) of our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly that their indeuour is, not to better, or to reforme the ſtate of religion, or the gouernment in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale (if ſo they can finde it may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) but farre otherwiſe, and not other, then vtterly to deſtroye, &amp; ſubuert both, <hi>Let vs breake &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly that their pride <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their eies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hartes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:42"/> they fight againſt the Lord, in ſtryuing with his annointed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1,"/> Firſt who ſeeth not in our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques an inſolent pride, and helliſh fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, who truſting in their forraine ſtrength abroad, and at home doe bray out into theſe ſpeaches or like to effect. <hi>This woman ſhall not raigne ouer vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc 19.14. Mat. 21.18.</note> 
               <hi>this is the laſt heire, come let vs kill her, and take awaye her inheritaunce. Come let vs rowſe vp Englande, and make a breache in it for vs, let vs ſette vp a king (or Queene rather) euen the ſonne of <hi>Tabeall,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 7.</note> 
               <hi>or that Idolatrous daughter.</hi> And who ſhall doe all this? Forſooth our Engliſh Catholiques, and theſe greedy greene youths muſt begin that attempt, that all the great, &amp; more graue, yet ſilent confederates maye fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they ſtirre vp, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Come on, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lmoſt no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>noe, is</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:43"/> 
               <hi>forme. Let vs. Let you?</hi> Why? ſeely wretches: what are you? <hi>What are we? Wee are the princes Pereles of the earth, wee are the Catholique confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates of the holy Church, wee are the ſufficient banded powers, able to eate vp all the heretickes in the land.</hi> Alas ſeely Caytiues, <hi>Parturiunt montes exit ridiculus mus.</hi> And doe you not knowe, that your triumph is before the victorye? Doe you not ſee that your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce doth repoſe his reſt, in the ſtrength farre ſhorte of helping heauen? and will you be confidently blind, &amp; not behold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of your vnnaturall ſubiects, in their treaſonable practiſes? doth not the pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſaye of ſuche, <hi>They are fallen, but we ſtand vpright,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 20. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>for wee truſt not in Charyots nor in horſes, or in the ſtrength of men, but in</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> But if ye thinke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> heart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:43"/> wheele &amp; compas of the heauens, which w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> glorious power, doth day by night (&amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for vs) encompaſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. And though ye be, the powers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole earth,<note place="margin">Eſay. 40.6.7.8.</note> &amp; the flowers therof, yet are ye but graſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> little creatures therin, yet of baſe repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord of hoaſts, ſhal arme them to his battaile, for vs his beloued Church, they ſhal beate you to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, &amp; wither you as heye. For when he hath ſet the ſeaſon &amp; day he wil then ſpeak to you in his diſpleaſure, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the weakeſt of theſe creatures, he can &amp; wil, as w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an iron rod, break al your popiſh power, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to peniſtone peeces: yea y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very gates of hell, cannot preuaile againſt him.<note place="margin">Ioel. 8.4.</note> The caterpiller (ſo eaſy to be cruſhed) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer worme, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graſhopper, the flie,<note place="margin">Amos. S. 6.17.24. Chro. 10.13.</note> the frogge, the louſe, &amp; matters of leſſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will he arme w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his power, &amp; then I ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſyrs? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:44"/> Lord of Hoaſts.<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Ye are kinges, yet not properly for the Lorde is the king of the vniuerſall earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>and hee giueth, and taketh away kings, &amp; kingdomes at his pleaſure, and giueth them to whom he will, euen to very abiects, if ſo he ſee it good.</hi> Let you, you: the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Antichriſt, let you creſt vp your Creſts, againſt the Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> In good truth ſirs, though ye be ſtrong by ſuttle ſleight to deceiue ſundry his ſeely ſeruaunts in his Church, yet ſhall you ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Captain <hi>Ioab</hi> (the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſure our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne <hi>Ieſus,</hi> for his <hi>Dauid</hi>) wil driue <hi>Abner</hi> and his Antichriſt <hi>Iſhboſeth</hi> quite out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> field.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 2.14. Pſal. 8.9. Apoc. 12.</note> But let you? The <hi>Dragon,</hi> &amp; his Angels of hell in earth, bend your battaile againſt Chriſt, our <hi>Michaell, <hi>and his annointed Prince, &amp; heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly powers in this his C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </hi> Well go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ye Gia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 7.10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 12.13.14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:44"/> cannot be ſtayed, riſe vp &amp; ſpare not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to play: <hi>For the Lorde hath whet his ſword, &amp; bent his bow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 2 14. Pſal. 7.10.11 12.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; meaneth to make a ſpeedy diſpatch of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutours, and he hath eſtabliſhed our <hi>Dauids</hi> throne, becauſe ſhee putteth her truſt in him.</hi> Therefore we reſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, in humble harts, that hee will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer her, <hi>And armeth vs againſt you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 22.</note> 
               <hi>with ſafetye of his good quarrell, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth vs by his heroicall ſpirite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">144.1.</note> 
               <hi>and maketh our fingers nimble for the battell Axe.</hi> Wherefore our true Engliſh hartes, doe not feare at all your Romaine force. Goe to then <hi>Abner</hi> thou <hi>Abington,</hi> and all the broode of Sathan, for our God for his Dauid <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> is encamped againſt thee, &amp; watcheth for the further protection,<note place="margin">127.1.</note> of our Engliſh <hi>Iſraell,</hi> whoſe holy name be bleſſed for euer, and euer <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> will further examine your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> former <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> on. <hi>Let</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:46"/> purpoſe, euen an vtter ſubuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this preſent ſtate, the religion of Chriſt, the Crowne, dignity, &amp; life of our moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> al which vnder theſe <hi>Metaphors</hi> coardes, &amp; bonds, phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes metonimicall, the ſcriptures giue to vs, and are before ſufficiently diſcerned. But oh miſerable Papiſtes, yee cannot break the bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds &amp; ſtaffe of liberty, which god in his great mercy hath made, with this his beloued Churche. It is not in your power, that appertaineth vnto God alone, to breake his league of loue with vs,<note place="margin">Zach. 11.8.14.15.</note> our bandes of Amitye and Chriſtian peace, to caſt out our ſhepheard, ſcatter the flocke, deſtroy the fruitfull paſture, &amp; all at once. It is not you, it is not you, except the Lorde for our vnthankfulnes doe enbattle you againſt vs, neither can you breake the leaſt coard of this Church or regiment, except you could bere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Maieſtye of her naturall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hom, God defend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpirite, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:46"/> And we with ſorrowfull ſighes knowe-that her dolerous death is your chiefe deſire. But how wicked is your atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, or howe vnable for Popiſh reach, ye no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing yet conſider. Wicked it is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the ſlaughter of her Maieſtye as Gods Scriptures woulde tell you, could ye beleeue them, &amp; your own tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling harts &amp; feebled hands, in ſo prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious a ſacrilege by you attempted doth bewray you to ſtriue herin, againſt your accuſing conſciences.<note place="margin">Ro. 2.</note> For haue we not this commaund in generall giuen to al fleſhe? <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> And is not the Princes perſon, garded w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall <hi>Prouiſo?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 105.15.</note> 
               <hi>Touch not mine annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nor doe my Prophetes no harme:</hi> Doth not God in Iuſtice threaten to require bloud for bloud, at the hand of euery murtherer?<note place="margin">Gen. 9.7.6.</note> And if men ſhedde the bloud of men, doth he not promiſe, that by men ſhall their bloud be ſhed again? Yea wicked <hi>Caine</hi> though curſed and excommunic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted from God, is marked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ulde ſlaye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> God is there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:47"/> not from his church in earth alone, but from his fauour &amp; loue, whoſe brothers bloud doth call for vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <hi>yet that man that killeth Caine, ſhalbe puniſhed ſeauen folde for that murther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>although it be done vpon ſo curſed a wretch.</hi> But for Princes, as they are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords annointed, ſo are they in a ſort incorporate into the ſhadow of Gods moſt ſacred perſon, &amp; maieſtically beare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Gods. <hi>Ego dixi dij eſtis,</hi> &amp; are ſo mightely garded by the Lorde,<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.</note> 
               <hi>That not onely his heauenly Angels are made their ſoldiours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 19. 2. Chr. 32.35</note> 
               <hi>againſt all their earthy &amp; infernall enemies, but alſo the Sun &amp; Moone, ſhalbe obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſ. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Yea the thundring Aire ſhall driue a terror to their cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped enimies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. K. 7.6.</note> 
               <hi>as if Chariot wheels did ſcoure the Coaſts, &amp; earth &amp; ſea ſhall ſend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuccour. Yea the birds of the Aire ſhall bewray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 10.80.</note> 
               <hi>the ſmalleſt worde ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to their diſhonor, &amp; the moſt ſecrete thought withi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the cloſet of our ſecre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>loſed.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:47"/> Maieſty, conſpiring hurt, to his annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted king. Drawe <hi>Dauids</hi> heart into thy boſome, &amp; ſet his lore be a law to thee, if thou wilt rightly fear y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had his ſoueraign in his hand (a man caſt of from God, &amp; excommunicate by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being king) &amp; <hi>Dauid</hi> now an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed as in his place to inioy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingly Crowne &amp; dignity, yet he would not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not (&amp; be guiltles) lay vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent hands vpon <hi>Saule,</hi> as yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords annointed. Nay whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> might haue ſlaine him or his ſeruaunts, which were more then willing therto, he onely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Caue cutte a peece of his garment, the which his face (when hee more deepely had conſidered) did mightely wound his ſoule as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtory reporteth. But to vſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of <hi>Saule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 24.6.</note> no man coulde perſwade <hi>Dauid</hi> becauſe hee was his Maiſter, his king, &amp; ſoueraign, &amp; now y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Lords annointed. For truely whoſoeuer ſhal ſtrike y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, of his ſoueraign, king <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Queen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> euen wound to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſtes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.34.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted
<pb facs="tcp:8973:48"/> of Chriſt Ieſus to bee done to himſelfe, how much more ſhall y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diuine Maieſtye on hie, for ſuch horrible bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed though onely done to his peculiar Image, his king on earth (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitng by him his own right arme to vs) accompt I ſay, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame as done vnto him ſelf. The conſideration herof, cauſed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Dauid</hi> to ſaye (being the next heire to <hi>Saule</hi> his Crowne, &amp; whoſe ſeruants al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hungred greatly <hi>Saules</hi> death in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor of <hi>Dauid</hi> their future king) <hi>The Lord keepe me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 26.9.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith hee, from doing that thing vnto my maiſter the Lords annointed,</hi> ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> ouercame his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place. A leſſon concerning ſuch future hopes, vpon whom, wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly many do depend, had they good right, yet ought they not to hearken to their falſe fauning paraſites to both their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowes, but to diſcountenaunce as traytors ſpeaches againſt the preſent <hi>Dauid,</hi> for the hope of a counterfeit <hi>Iſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boſeth,</hi> al ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they diſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> deadly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cond
<pb facs="tcp:8973:48"/> time when <hi>Saule</hi> was caſt into a dead ſleep &amp; all his Camp, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his hungry <hi>Abyſhay,</hi> entred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilion, &amp; tooke away his ſpear from his beds head, <hi>Abner</hi> and the hoaſt lying on ſleepe about him (looke to thy watch more faithfully <hi>Abner</hi>) God hath cloſed thine enimye (ſaith <hi>Abyſhay</hi> to <hi>Dauid</hi>) into thy hands this day therfore I pray thee let me ſmite him once w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſpeare, &amp; I wil not ſmite him, again (his meaning was he would kill him at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt blowe) to <hi>Abyſhay Dauid</hi> ſaid, deſtroy him not. His reaſon why is,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 26.9</note> for who can ſaye his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords annointed &amp; be giltles? No, neither <hi>Samuell</hi> can commaund it, nor <hi>Dauid</hi> the future annointed may do it, much leſſe ambitious <hi>Abyſhay,</hi> can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, or any other perſon, to bereue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> priuate hand the Lords annointed of his life, and bee without daunger, nay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation of the deepeſt treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſauage ſlaughter that poſſibly can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of God and of naturall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; ſure I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his
<pb facs="tcp:8973:49"/> the king. Oh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our Catholique Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors would thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> had as much holines, &amp; <hi>Samuell,</hi> &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Apoſtles had as great aucthoritye, &amp; more, then any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop can haue, and yet theſe neuer did or durſt, leaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people to their liberty, but brought them vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bands &amp; (coardes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Princely gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) yea &amp; vnto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Princes, &amp; were ſo fart from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding or procuring violent handes vpon ſuch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords Chriſts, as on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, they called all chriſtians into due obedience to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to moſt willing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, teaching &amp; threatning gods hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy iudgement, to all the tranſgreſſors. And now though I haue tried lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g your patience in this profitable diſcourſe, yet I ſee (me thinketh) a willing minde in you, to heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt breach of this our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſhew by proofe, how vain it is for the vnnaturall ſubiect to riſe to the ruine of his liege and natural king, and how vnable they be to bring their ſhamefull indeuour to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rowful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ende. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> blinde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:49"/> chiefly aime at the heart of our <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi> But the euent doth prooue, that as God for <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſo our king Chriſt for his holy annointed, doth take this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike treaſon as doone vnto himſelfe, and therefore in vaine is all your toyle in treaſonable affaires.</p>
            <p>To our ſingular comforte, lette vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member theſe wordes of our text, <hi>Why doe ye murmur, &amp;c.</hi> In vaine, in vain, yea, and that in a double vanitie, doe our Papiſts conſpire and rage. For neither ſhall they bee able to hurt our gratious Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> nor yet be able to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide Gods heauie diſpleaſure by the hand of her authoritie. They ſhall neuer preuaile in their attempt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.2.9.</note> for theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons following: Firſt, whoſoeuer ſette themſelues againſt an abſolute power, armed of God, muſt needs be ouercome, but the Catholike traytors do ſo, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ſaid: <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe when the purpoſes of earthly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the decree of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt needes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.7.8.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:50"/> are ſo bent: <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eternal decree is ſette downe in this Pſalme. Firſt, for the Lord Chriſt in his Church, that hee ſhall raigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the kinges of the earth for euer, and nexte, for his annointed Princes, that they ſhall raigne in his <hi>Syon,</hi> vnder him their Lorde and king, maugre their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, during his time limited for them.</p>
            <p>Therefore neyther <hi>Reſyn,</hi> nor hys partner <hi>Romelia,</hi> nor yet the purpoſed ſonne of <hi>Tabeall,</hi> canne preuayle againſt <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 7.</note> nor his <hi>Dauid.</hi> For Gods decree hath ſaide <hi>(It ſhall not bee)</hi> how cunning, mightie, or Catholike ſoeuer hee the conſpiracie: for earthlie councel cannot preuayle againſt the Lorde. So as to our ſingular comfortes, and Gods eternall praiſe (beloued in Chriſt) wee may ſafely apply this ſaying of our moſt louing GOD, to our Church, and kingdome, becauſe through his greate mercie,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> wee are a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vnyuerſall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> net<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:50"/> 
               <hi>All thy Children ſhall bee taught of GOD,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 54.13.14, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>and much peace ſhall bee to thy Children. In righteouſneſſe ſhalt thou bee eſtabliſhed, and bee free from oppreſſion and from feare: For it ſhall not come neare thee, beholde the enemie ſhall gather himſelfe, but without me. Whoſoeuer ſhal gather himſelfe in thee againſt mee, ſhal fall: Beholde, I haue created the Smyth that bloweth the coales in the fire, and hym that bringeth foorth an Inſtrument for hys woorke, and I haue created the deſtroyer to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye, but all the weapons that are made againſt thee ſhall not proſper, and euerie tongue that ſhall ryſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>halt condemne. This is the heritage of the Lords ſeruants, and the righteouſneſſe is of me ſayth the Lord</hi> This is the ſtaffe of our ſtay, and the ſtrength of our arme, euen the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iolable decree for his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vs ſtyll to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> fully nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de, ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:51"/> many ſtraungers, as hunger the Lordes milke without guile, in this his <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nurcerie. In vaine therefore ſhall bee your trecherous attemptes againſt her Maieſtie, this Church, and kingdome, though hell be come to your helpe. And therefore O Lorde, wee offer vnto thee the Calues of our lippes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe. 14.2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb. 13.15</note> and euer mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie thy holy name. This decree being for vs, howe can the Papiſtes or their Treaſons be vnreuenged. God ſayth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting their proper nature, the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall riſe, but he ſayth ſtraightway they ſhall fall. <hi>Their tongues ſhal raile, but wee by truth in God ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them. They ſhal gather them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but ſhal not finde vs alone, for the Lord raigneth in <hi>Syon,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 99.1.</note> 
               <hi>be the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple neuer ſo vnpatient: He will ariſe, and his enemies ſhal be ſcattered, and as ſmoke in the wind,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ſal. 68.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; <hi>waxe againſt the Sunne, ſo ſhall they melte and flye before him.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Examples <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>finite: for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Lorde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:51"/> Princes, when they ſtoode in neede of him? When men ſhall be required, his <hi>300.</hi> for his <hi>Gedeon,</hi> ſhall put to flyght his <hi>Medianites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 7</note> that are exceeding num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. His haile-ſtones ſhall beat to death ſuch enemies, as with-ſtande his <hi>Ioſua.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſua. 10.</note> And the ayrie winde ſhall ruſſle trees, whereon God doth walke before <hi>Dauid</hi> to his battaile,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 5.24.</note> to yeelde him victorie. <hi>Architophel</hi> ſhall ſlaye himſelfe, as did <hi>Bellamie,</hi> and Gods vengeance cannot ſuffer the graceleſſe <hi>Abſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lon</hi> to die a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon death. The trees therefore ſhal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute his pride, his ſhagged haire &amp; this Spanyels cutte) ſhalbe his halter. And to omit the Scriptures teſtimonie for <hi>Dauid,</hi> if we looke vppon Gods preſent iudgements in this our nation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time, againſt all traiterous aſſay, in all ſorts and callings, we ſhall bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to conclude, that all in vaine is their attempt, when they without God, gather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ſelues againſt theyr So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> wil affoord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the
<pb facs="tcp:8973:52"/> 
               <hi>Oſbert</hi> of <hi>London</hi> and his <hi>50.</hi> thouſande Traytors,<note place="margin">An. 1196. Rich. 2.</note> againſt king <hi>Richard <hi>2.</hi>
               </hi> were ſpeedily ouerthrown, and he their chief, executed at the Elmes, it maye bee the place of the laſt execution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Spalding</hi> betrayed <hi>Barwicke</hi> to the <hi>Scottes,</hi> and was by the king of <hi>Scots</hi> cauſed to be hanged, becauſe of his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt his naturall kyng <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roger Mortimer</hi> conſpyring the death of king <hi>Edw. <hi>3.</hi>
               </hi> his Father,<note place="margin">An. 1317.</note> was hanged at the foreſaid Elmes.</p>
            <p>And that notable rable of Rakehels, <hi>Iacke Strawe,</hi> and <hi>Wat Tyler,</hi> that ſpoiled <hi>London,</hi> and ſlew the Counſaile, bearing bloodie hand againſt all authoritie and learning (ſo that vppon whom ſoeuer a penne and yncke was founde, he dyed in their tyrannous Treaſon) had yet their deſertes: For <hi>W. Walworth</hi> the Maior of this noble Citie of <hi>London<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> arreſted him with the mace of deat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>The hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> conti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8973:52"/>
            <p>The perilous treaſons by them pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, ioyned iuſt with the preſente Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike attemptes, as <hi>Iacke Strawe</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed at his death.</p>
            <p>They meant to haue ſlaine aſwell the king as his Counſaile, the Lordes and Gentlemen of accompt, the Biſhops &amp; Preachers of the Land, all Iudges and common Lawyers, onely the begging Friers (aunceſtors of our preſent Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites) ſhould haue beene the Curates of the Country. And kinges ſhoulde haue bene raiſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Tilekil for <hi>Wat Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> was decreed the king of <hi>Kent,</hi> &amp; ſo in euery ſhire ſuch another. And becauſe they were miſerable beggars, their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was to haue burned the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> at the foure corners thereof, and ſo to haue eaſilye gathered her wealth vnto themſelues. But thankes be vnto God, as the purpoſes of theſe former Papiſtes with theſe our preſent Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lone in effect, &amp; very reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Lords lot, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idge hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> goe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:53"/> and ſpend the day in like examples. As in <hi>Hen. <hi>4.</hi>
               </hi> time, how his vnnatural No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, with their traiterous Prieſt <hi>Madeline</hi> (for it is a ſtraunge treaſon, where neither the Pope nor his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines be partakers) by the good ſeruice of his Subiects of <hi>Circeſter,</hi> were taken the moſt of them, and put to death. And though the Rebelles ſette fire on the towne, ſuppoſing that way to withdraw their ſeruice, yet in loue to their loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſeruice to their Lord and king, they did perſiſte to proſecute the trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Rebels, and their attendantes, to their deſerued death. But to let al other Princes paſſe vs, would God our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes could beholde his mightie hande for our <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What conſpiracies haue they had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her maieſtie, which Gods maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie hath not reuealed to her, that the wheele of Iuſtice might rewarde them. <hi>Plometry</hi> the prieſt,<note place="margin">1570..</note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erats at <hi>Durham</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>thumb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:53"/> Doctor <hi>Story,</hi> with <hi>Haunce</hi> that fooliſh prieſt, and table gameſter (ſuch was his profeſſion and common practiſe) <hi>Campi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and his fellow champions, <hi>Arden, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meruile, Throgmorton,</hi> and the reſt, with their trayterous Printer, all which in wonderfull wiſe the Lorde hath laide o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the worlde, and by perfect trials, as by their own confeſſions, were found deepely dyed in moſt deadly Treaſons, and as moſt wicked weedes, were iuſtly caſt out of our Chriſtian garden.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe (beloued) this moſte odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and execrable purpoſe, by <hi>Sauage,</hi> and other Sathanicall ſeede, ſo ſecretlie deuyſed, and being Imps of very green youth, and ſome of them as ſprouts ſpred into her maieſties Court, were therfore for the moſt parte, leaſt ſuſpected of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, which threatned this Nation more imminent danger: Yet our euerlaſting watchman, the Lord <hi>Iehouah,</hi> from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> did ſo ryng a ſtil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atter,<note place="margin">Pſal. 127.1.</note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> theyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:54"/> to Gods great glorie, her maieſties ſtill preſeruation, the Churches peace, &amp; <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> tranquility, they were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith) and the godly wiſedome of the Prince,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> by the cenſure of equitie, hath for the peace of her Subiectes, and her bounden dutie vnto God, cropped ſome of theſe bitter braunches from the tree of this common wealth, whoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour was (might they haue attained their intent) to haue pulſed vp the ſame by the verie rootes.</p>
            <p>Oh ſauage crueltie, an ill deuiſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, for ſo long ſuffering &amp; prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clemencie extended from her meeke maieſtie amongſt you. And whereas the reſt apprehended, remaine heere and els where: ſo I beſeech God in mercie, if it be his good wil, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert their ſoules, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſeeing the valour of their infernall ſinnes, may ſpeedily repente them, wyth teares and wordes fitte for repentance, to the comfort o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauncement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>techriſt, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:54"/> cut from the City of the Lord, &amp; that the bryar and bramble buſh of <hi>Rome</hi> and Poperie (the field and forreſt of treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) againſt Chriſtian kinges &amp; kingdomes, maye bee diſcerned and deſpiſed by the Cedars of our Libanus,<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.8.14</note> ſo as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt honourable aſſemblye of our beſt choſen plantes, euen with whole conſente, her Maieſties ſworde may bee fully ſette in edge, and her gratious arme, by theyr godly ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, ſo yet further armed, that ſhe may vowe, and ſing to God with the former <hi>Dauid: Betimes I wil deſtroye all the wicked in the lande,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 101.8.</note> 
               <hi>that I may cut off all the workers of iniquitie from the Citie of the Lord.</hi> And before the meetings of this moſt honourable Court (brethren) lette vs giue the Lord no reſt, vntil he haue mercie, &amp; ſurely ſet in ſafetie, our <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 62.7</note> the praiſe of the world. And that in our daies <hi>Darius</hi> ſtatute bee reuiued: namely, that Gods hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may be more &amp; more richly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſe,<note place="margin">Eſra. 6.</note> his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cere godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:55"/> to God by her good Subiectes, for her proſperous Raigne, increaſing Peace, Regall Throne, honour to her ſacred perſon and ioye to her ſanctified ſoule. And that her olde daies may growe in health, and godlines, to double the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of her graces yeares, to the fulnes of good chriſtians comfort in Chriſt our Lorde, if it may ſtande with his bleſſed will &amp; good pleaſure. So ſhall our mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring Papiſtes at home, and their banded confederates abroade, mourne and houle, becauſe the Lord doth meete them in the fielde, and their attemptes, by his great ſtrength, are brought to be but vaine. Be wiſe therefore ye kinges and be learned ye mighty wights of the worlde, ſee and conſider, and ſerue the Lorde in feare, and reioyce in him, and not in his aduerſarye at <hi>Rome.</hi> And you common Catholiques and reſolute tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, ſeeke no longer to cruſhe, but kiſſe the ſonne of God (decreed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his vniuerſall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> loue, honou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> annoint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8973:55"/> in your inuentions, for the Lorde will haue her to pertake of <hi>Dauids</hi> ſolace o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſaying with mighty conqueſt, <hi>Moab is my waſhpot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 60.8.</note> 
               <hi>ouer Edome will I caſt out my ſhoe, vpon Philiſtia will I triumph.</hi> He will vſe his liberty ouer them, in his victory, &amp; put them to vile ſeruitude, and then toſſed &amp; troubled <hi>England,</hi> repoſe thy confidence in Chriſt, and imbrace not his grace in vaine, ſo ſhall he make thee the praiſe of the world, and thy <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the beauty of Chriſtian Princes, for the glorye of his name, to whom with God the father and the holy Ghoſt, be all prayſe, power dominion, and immortall thankes tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout all generations. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
